<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Lecture Notes]]></title><description><![CDATA[Obsidian digital garden]]></description><link>http://github.com/dylang/node-rss</link><image><url>site-lib/media/favicon.png</url><title>Lecture Notes</title><link/></image><generator>Webpage HTML Export plugin for Obsidian</generator><lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 01:42:38 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="site-lib/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 01:42:37 GMT</pubDate><ttl>60</ttl><dc:creator/><item><title><![CDATA[03. Neural Word Representation]]></title><description><![CDATA[NLP has undergone a major transformation over the past few decades, shifting from traditional statistical methods to modern neural network-based approaches.Early NLP systems relied heavily on statistical language models (SLMs). These models estimate the probability of a word sequence based on observed frequencies in large text corpora. N-gram models is one of the most common approaches, which predict the next word given the previous n−1 words. For example, a trigram model predicts the next word based on the previous two words.However, SLMs have limitations about data sparsity, context window, and feature engineering (SLMs often required manual preprocessing and feature extraction).In the part, we will focus on neural network based methods.Word Embedding is one of Dense Embeddings. Dense vector has the following advantages: Short vectors may be easier to use as features in machine learning (less weights to tune) Dense vectors may generalize better than storing explicit counts They may do better at capturing synonymy: car and automobile are synonyms; but are distinct dimensions
a word with car as a neighbor and a word with automobile as a neighbor should be similar, but aren’t In practice, they appear to work better So can we convert one-hot (Sparse) to Dense Embeddings? Assume there is a matrix W. We can multiply our one-hot with W. This gives us the “embedding” for a word. W is what we need to learn (in the context of machine learning).
Please read Q&amp;A for more details. Word2Vec CBOW Skip-gram Negative sampling Fasttext character representation Glove Q: What is the relationship between the corpus-based approach and feature engineering? A: In traditional Corpus-based Approaches to NLP, feature extraction is an explicit process. This feature extraction defines the features used by the statistical model, such as the word ID, case, and POS tags (e.g., Word: 546; Case: Upper-case; POS: NN). In Deep Learning Approaches, the input text still undergoes feature extraction, but the output is a dense binary vector (e.g., 10010010010101). Therefore, feature engineering is the traditional method of explicit feature extraction from the corpus, which has been largely replaced by automatic feature learning in deep learning.Q: What is an important property of word embeddings? A: An important property of word embeddings is that semantic similar words should have similar representation. This concept is tied to J.R. Firth’s 1953 dictum: “You shall know a word by the company it keeps!”.Q: What determines the size of one-hot embeddings? A: The size, or dimension, of a one-hot encoding vector is determined by the vocabulary size.Q: What is an advantage of dense embeddings? A: Dense vectors have several advantages: they are short vectors, may generalize better, and appear to work better in practice, especially at capturing synonymy.Q: What is a problem with n-gram models? A: A major problem with statistical N-gram models is that most longer word sequences have not been seen in the corpus. This requires a non-satisfactory solution like back-off to a shorter sequence. N-gram models also operate in Discrete Space.Q: Why do we call the Feed Forward Neural Network here self-supervised? A: The Feed Forward Neural Network language model is considered self-supervised because training needs only unlabelled data (pure text). The model is trained to predict the next word given previous words. The meaning of the word is important for estimating the next word, and this meaning needs to be encoded in the embedding.Q: What is the advantage of a continuous space? A: The advantage of mapping words to a continuous word representation is generalization to similar n-grams. Unlike discrete space, which only allows for exact matching, continuous space enables the model to automatically learn optimal features and find the nearest neighbor, capturing syntactic similarities and semantic similarities.Q: Is the position of the input words important? A: For the Continuous Bag of Words Model (CBOW), the position of the input words is ignored. The model sums the surrounding words to predict the center word.Q: How many embeddings do we get for each word? A: For Word2Vec models (CBOW and Skip-gram), typically there is one embedding for each word.
More details: <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://lilianweng.github.io/posts/2017-10-15-word-embedding/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://lilianweng.github.io/posts/2017-10-15-word-embedding/" target="_self">Learning Word Embedding</a> <br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://medium.com/@fraidoonomarzai99/word2vec-cbow-skip-gram-in-depth-88d9cc340a50" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://medium.com/@fraidoonomarzai99/word2vec-cbow-skip-gram-in-depth-88d9cc340a50" target="_self">Word2Vec (CBOW, Skip-gram) In Depth</a> Q: What is the CBOW score function based on? A: The CBOW score function is based on the dot product to measure similarity.Q: What is the difference between CBOW and Skip-gram? A: CBOW and Skip-gram have opposite objectives:
CBOW predicts the word based on surrounding words.
Skip-gram predicts the surrounding words given the current word.
Q: What is maximized with the Skip-gram objective? A: The Skip-gram objective is to maximize the probability of any context word given the current word. This objective uses a negative log loss.Q: Why is negative sampling necessary? A: Negative sampling is necessary because the standard Skip-gram objective requires normalization over the entire vocabulary, which is computationally demanding. Negative sampling resolves this by generating samples and summing over those samples instead of the entire vocabulary.
Q: Why do we use sigmoid instead of softmax in the objective function? A: We use the Sigmoid function () because negative sampling converts the problem from a multiclass classifier to a binary classifier.Q: Where do we get negative examples from? A: Negative examples are sampled from the lexicon. The negative set typically contains 2 to 20 words sampled from some distribution, such as uniform, unigram, or a smoothed unigram. The smoothed unigram distribution is created by raising the probabilities to the power of and then renormalizing.Q: For a corpus with fixed size, are there more unique 6-grams or 3-grams? A: Based on the problem of N-gram models—that most longer word sequences have not been seen—it can be inferred that there would be more unique 6-grams than 3-grams, as longer sequences lead to higher sparsity.Q: How are context and target words represented with FastText? A: FastText uses character N-grams:A: FastText uses character N-grams:
The word embedding for the target word is the sum of character 3-grams to 6-grams and the whole word itself.
The word embedding for the context word is taken from the embedding table without adding character n-grams.
Q: What is the difference between Word2Vec and FastText? A: FastText is an extension of Word2Vec that addresses challenges found in Word2Vec. FastText uses subword representation (character n-grams) to solve issues in morphologically rich languages and to create representations for words that have not been seen previously.Q: What is a key difference between Word2Vec and GloVe? A: The key difference lies in the perspective used for training: Word2Vec uses a Local view (predicting words within the context), while GloVe uses a Global view. GloVe leverages Word co-occurrence matrices and is motivated by the ratio of co-occurrence probabilities.Q: In which situations does GloVe likely produce unreliable word embeddings?
Rare words – too few co-occurrences to learn meaningful vectors.
Small corpus – global statistics are sparse and noisy.
Domain mismatch – training domain differs from the target domain.
Polysemous words – one vector cannot represent multiple senses.
No subword modeling – fails on morphology and misspellings.
Out-of-vocabulary words – no embeddings for unseen words.
Biased training data – co-occurrence statistics reflect and amplify bias.
]]></description><link>natural-language-processing/03.-neural-word-representation.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Natural Language Processing/03. Neural Word Representation.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 01:42:20 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[02. Words]]></title><description><![CDATA[Example (Chinese): 我看书 — “I read/look at a book.”. Morphemes:
我 = I
看 = read/look
书 = book
Key idea: Minimal or no inflection; morphemes usually stand alone.Example (Turkish): ev-ler-in-de — “in your houses”. Morphemes:
ev = house
-ler = plural
-in = your
-de = in
Key idea: Morphemes have clear boundaries and single meanings, attached in sequence.Example (Spanish): habl-o — “I speak”. Morphemes:
habl- = speak
-o = 1st person + singular + present
Key idea: A single morpheme typically encodes multiple grammatical features.Example (Inuktitut): tusaatsiarunnanngittualuujunga — “I really can’t hear well”. Simplified morphemes:
tusaa- = hear
-tsiaq- = well
-junnaq- = be able
-nngit- = not
-tualuu- = very
-junga = I
Key idea: Many morphemes combine to express what would be a whole sentence.Example (Arabic): kitaab — “book”. Morphemes:
k-t-b = root “write”
i__a__ = vocalic pattern forming a noun
Key idea: Words are formed by inserting vocalic patterns into consonantal roots.
Lexeme, e.g., SEE
Word-form, e.g., saw, seeing, saws
Paradigm, e.g., I, my, mine, me
Word family, e.g., act, action, actor, activate, active, activist Lexical/Content
Functional
Root Suffix
Prefix
Infix
Circumfix Changes the grammatical form of a word without creating a new lexeme.
Does not change core meaning or word class.
Typical categories: tense, number, case, agreement.
Examples:
walk → walks (3sg)
cat → cats (plural)
see → saw (past) Forms a new word (new lexeme) by adding derivational affixes.
Often changes meaning and sometimes word class.
Examples:
happy → unhappy
nation → national
modern → modernize
read → reader Combines two or more roots/words to form a new lexeme.
The components remain recognizable.
Examples:
black + board → blackboard
sun + light → sunlight
ice + cream → ice-cream
Here’s a concise English note summarizing the morphological processes you listed, with clear examples:
Maps a word form to its lemma (dictionary/base form).
Ignores context.
Example:
saw → see Lemma and Lexeme are different. Lexeme is an abstract concept, while lemma is a concrete concept. Breaks a word into (lemma + grammatical tag).
Does not consider context, so may produce multiple analyses.
Example:
saw → {(see, verb.past), (saw, noun.sg)} Uses context to select the correct analysis.
Example:
Sentence: Peter saw her
saw → {(see, verb.past)} Splits a word into its smallest meaningful units (morphemes).
Example:
de-nation-al-iz-ation → de + nation + al + iz + ation Produces a word form from a lemma + features.
Essentially the reverse of lemmatization.
Example:
(see, verb.past) → saw
Both Feature Engineering (FE) and Representation Learning (RL) are methodologies designed to solve the critical challenge in machine learning models: how to map text into a fixed vector representation, or .However, they differ fundamentally in their approach, timeframe, and resulting data structure.Feature Engineering (FE) represents the dominant methods used over the last 25 years. This approach relies on manually defined templates to describe the important information of the text. FE is often decried as “costly, hand-crafted, expensive, domain-specific,” among other criticisms. While simple features typically give the bulk of the performance and can yield high accuracies, the feature set is still difficult to maintain.Representation Learning (RL) describes the methods developed over the last 10 years. The defining characteristic of RL is that the features are automatically learned. The result of this process is an approximation, meaning some information are lost, and the representation is typically task dependent.The methodologies lead to stark differences in the resulting vector format:
FE commonly uses representations like the Bag of Words (BoW). This approach results in a Sparse matrix, where most entries are zero. BoW uses one feature per word, which can be a Binary feature (0 or 1) or a Count feature. Feature Importance and TF-IDF can help solve problems respectively about word importance and high-frequently used no-meaning words.
RL generates a Neural representation, which is characterized as Dense. Negation: It's not a great monster movie.
Different sense: There's a great deal of corny dialogue and preposterous moments.
Multiple sentiments: A great ensemble cast can't lift this heartfelt enterprise out of the familiar.
Number of features: Too few. Hard to distinguish different inputs
Too many. Overfitting Representation Learning evolved to better handle critical challenges inherent in text data that constrained Feature Engineering:
Word Order and Length: FE methods like BoW ignore word position when dealing with variable length input. Although FE can use Higher-Order Binary Feature Templates (like bigrams or trigrams) to consider word order and maintain a fixed size vector representation, this introduces the challenge of an extremely large number of features. Conversely, RL must address the fact that word order is important and must handle variable length input.
Open Vocabulary: For FE, open vocabulary is a challenge that requires the use of a fixed vocab. RL also faces the open vocabulary challenge, but aims to solve it by being able to understand unknown words, such as the complex term Hippopotomonstrosesquipedaliophobia.
Granularity: RL’s approach to solving vocabulary challenges involves identifying the best granularity—choosing among words, subwords, or characters. RL acknowledges that while using characters provides much training data and allows understanding of unknown words, it leads to long sequences for text, which is not efficient. Therefore, RL uses machine learning based subword segmentation to learn efficient representation. Techniques like Byte-Pair Encoding (BPE), which starts with an Initial vocabulary of characters to ensure every words can be represented, are employed to strike this balance.
]]></description><link>natural-language-processing/02.-words.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Natural Language Processing/02. Words.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 01:29:45 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[01. Introduction]]></title><description><![CDATA[NLP: Algorithms to process, analyze and understand texts in natural language
Understanding structure
Understanding meaning Ambiguity, e.g., bank
Compositionality, e.g., green thumb
Co-reference, e.g., if the baby does not like the milk, boil it
Living language, e.g., Eyjafjallajökull
Rare events
<img alt="Pasted image 20251126022044.png" src="attachments/pasted-image-20251126022044.png" target="_self">
Corpus = large collection of annotated texts (or speech files)
Linguistics
Machine learning
NLP tasks: Information Extraction + Retrieval
Summarization
Machine translation
Question Answering
Personal assistant NLP techniques (focus on deep learning-based): Data types Texts, e.g., Brown Corpus, Penn Treebank
Dictionaries/Ontologies, e.g., WordNet, GermaNet, EuroWordNet Data grows English Text Corpora (News)
Computer MT or ASR systems train on &gt;&gt; 1GWords. News Shuffle, GigaWord, Europarl, VideoLectures, …
Human speaks 0.5 GigaWords in a Lifetime! Model types Classification, e.g., word sense disambiguation
Sequence Classification, e.g., sentiment analysis
Sequence labeling, e.g., named entity recognition
Sequence to Sequence model, e.g., summerization
Structure prediction, e.g., parsing Evaluation: Human evaluation
Automatic evaluation ]]></description><link>natural-language-processing/01.-introduction.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Natural Language Processing/01. Introduction.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 01:20:46 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="."&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Home]]></title><description><![CDATA[This is where I take notes.]]></description><link>index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">index.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 01:18:56 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>