<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Yulei's Notes]]></title><description><![CDATA[Obsidian digital garden]]></description><link>http://github.com/dylang/node-rss</link><image><url>site-lib/media/favicon.png</url><title>Yulei's Notes</title><link/></image><generator>Webpage HTML Export plugin for Obsidian</generator><lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 20:34:18 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="site-lib/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 20:34:18 GMT</pubDate><ttl>60</ttl><dc:creator/><item><title><![CDATA[01. Introduction]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img alt="Pasted image 20251126031843.png" src="attachments/pasted-image-20251126031843.png" target="_self">
Generated by NotebookLM.
The primary rationale for MDSD is to manage the increasing complexity of software development. MDSD specifically targets accidental complexity (such as platform complexity). It continues the historical trend of increasing abstraction by enabling models to replace objects.The main goals of MDSD include:
Achieving a higher level of abstraction and platform independence.
Increasing development speed and software quality.
Improving reuse, avoiding redundancy, and better managing technological changes.
Automation through model transformations.
Modeling is a fundamental part of informatics, serving a crucial epistemological role: the idea behind scientific modeling is to represent and increase information. Knowledge and information in informatics are always processed using models.The formal definition is derived from Herbert Stachowiak’s General Model Theory.Models, according to Stachowiak, are characterized by three features:
Mapping Feature: Models are mappings from, or representations of, natural or artificial originals.
Reduction Feature: Models capture only the attributes relevant to their users/creators, generally not all attributes of the original.
Pragmatic Feature: Models fulfill their function only for particular subjects (users), time intervals, and specific operations.
In MDSD, the system under development is the original, and different models represent different attributes. For example:
A component model (PCM) represents the software architecture.
A class diagram (UML) represents the object-oriented structure.
Program code represents the structure and behaviour (execution semantics) of the system.
Performance simulation results represent timing behaviour and resource usage.
These terms distinguish the scope and standardization level of model usage in development:<br><img alt="Pasted image 20251126031934.png" src="attachments/pasted-image-20251126031934.png" target="_self">MDA is an OMG initiative proposing non-proprietary standards to realize model-driven development using automated transformations. The process is defined by three main model types:
Computation Independent Model (CIM): Describes requirements and the system environment; details of the system are hidden. (Example: UML use case diagram).
Platform Independent Model (PIM): Focuses on system operation; platform-specific details are hidden. This part does not change between platforms. (Example: A component model).
Platform Specific Model (PSM): Adds focus on the details of using a specific platform. (Example: A class diagram tailored to a platform).
Application:
The MDA process involves automated transformations between PIMs and PSMs, often incorporating a separate Platform Model. Ultimately, the PSM is transformed into Code. The vision is that specifications should be machine readable and that models should be transformed into other models. While the ideal vision suggests that domain experts create models from which code is generated, the current pragmatic MDSD approach often relies heavily on partial code generation and separates generic, repetitive, and individual code.]]></description><link>model-driven-software-development/01.-introduction.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Model-Driven Software Development/01. Introduction.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 15:44:58 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="."&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Home]]></title><description><![CDATA[This is where I take notes.]]></description><link>index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">index.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 02:30:49 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[03. Advanced UML]]></title><description><![CDATA[
Core PrimitiveTypes, pre-defined types Integer, Boolean, String, UnlimitedNatural Basic, central notions such as class, attributes, operation, package Abstractions,&nbsp;concepts such as&nbsp;generalization, instantiation, restriction, cardinality, etc. Generalization Generalization sets overlapping (default) / disjoint incomplete (default) / complete Power types Constructs, base concept - association Profiles stereotype metaclass Generated by NotebookLM.
The Unified Modeling Language (UML) utilizes profiles and stereotypes as built-in extension mechanisms because UML, while a general-purpose language, is not ideal for all purposes.UML Profiles: A profile is applied to extend a reference metamodel (such as UML) or to adapt it to a specific platform, domain, or method.
Definition and Constraint: A profile is a package that extends elements of the type Metaclass and may add additional constraints. Profiles are intrinsically tied to a reference metamodel created using the Meta Object Facility (MOF) (e.g., UML or PCM) and cannot be defined as standalone packages.
Application: Profile application is a type of package import. One or more profiles can be applied to a package. Profiles are optional, but if application is mandatory, the keyword {required} can be used.
Content: A profile can contain data types, classes, stereotypes, primitive types, and enumerations. It also has the ability to re-use or extend parts of other profiles.
UML Stereotypes: Stereotypes are considered the most crucial extension elements.
Definition: A stereotype is defined as a class within the profiles package that specifies how a class in the reference metamodel can be extended.
Application (Extension): When a profile is applied, the stereotypes it contains may be applied to classes. The application of a stereotype to a class is specifically termed extension, and it is graphically represented by a solid, filled arrow.
Properties: Stereotypes can include attributes, which are referred to as tags. The corresponding values of a stereotype instance are known as tagged values. Stereotypes cannot be extended by other stereotypes.
<img alt="Pasted image 20251126032448.png" src="attachments/pasted-image-20251126032448.png" target="_self">The decision between extending the existing UML metamodel via profiles or creating a separate custom MOF-based metamodel often positions profiles as a middle path.Creating a UML Profile (Extension): Profiles are considered a "light-weight" method for adapting and extending existing metamodels at level M2. This approach is advantageous when:
Reuse is prioritized: Concepts such as components, classes, and others can be reused from the existing UML structure.
Validity is critical: Models remain valid UML instances. The semantics of UML are also valid for the extended models.
Dynamic Application: Profiles can be applied dynamically to models.
Tool Compatibility: Existing UML tools can still be utilized for modeling the extended models.
Creating a Custom Metamodel: This approach is necessary when greater flexibility and complete freedom in modeling are required.
High Flexibility: Custom metamodels offer more flexibility compared to profiles.
Total Freedom: They provide total freedom in modeling.
Drawbacks and Judgment:
Profile Limitations: Profiles offer lower flexibility because all concepts of UML are still inherited and remain valid, even if those concepts have no meaning within the specific domain being modeled. Furthermore, profiles cannot modify existing metamodels; they can only extend them via stereotypes.
Custom Metamodel Limitations: This approach leads to little re-use, meaning concepts (like the component concept) must be re-defined entirely.
Ultimately, there is no universal guideline for this decision; rather, it hinges entirely on the specific set of adaptations necessary for the existing reference metamodel.The basic structure of UML 2.4 is defined within the UML Infrastructure Library. This library defines a meta-language core that is employed to define UML itself and other related metamodels.The Infrastructure Library consists of two core packages: Core: Contains the basic concepts necessary for metamodeling. The Core package is further divided into several sub-packages: PrimitiveTypes: Defines pre-defined types such as Boolean, Integer, String, and UnlimitedNatural.
Basic: Contains central notions like package, class, operation, and attribute.
Abstractions: Includes concepts such as instantiation, generalization, cardinality, and restriction.
Constructs: Contains the base concept of association. Profiles: Contains the necessary mechanisms for adaptation. This architecture ensures the architectural alignment of MOF, UML, and XMI (used for exchanging models).UML generalization techniques center on Generalization Sets, which define specific partitions of generalization associations. Generalization (or Inheritance) is a taxonomic relation where a more special classifier inherits all features of the more general classifier, meaning every instance of the special classifier is also an indirect instance of the general classifier.There are four partitionings available in UML 2 that can be used within a Generalization Set:Application of Generalization Sets: Generalization sets are utilized to model inheritance hierarchies that possess multiple dimensions and precise restrictions.For instance, consider a Locomotive class:
Motive Power: The first dimension, motive power, might partition Locomotive into Steam Locomotive and Motor Locomotive. This set could be labeled {disjoint, complete} to indicate that a locomotive must belong to exactly one of these two categories.
Motor Type: The Motor Locomotive class could then be partitioned by motor type into Electric Locomotive and Internal Combustion Locomotive. This set might be labeled {overlapping, complete}, indicating that while all types are specified, a locomotive could potentially belong to both (e.g., a hybrid locomotive).
A power type is defined as a class whose instances are subclasses.
Inspiration: The concept was derived from the mathematical notion of a power set, which is a set whose instances are subsets.
Relation to Generalization Sets: A Generalization Set can optionally be linked to a type, and this type is then referred to as a power type.
Function: The instances of this power type are the subclasses of the class that the generalization set describes in further detail.
Layer Limitation: Power types are useful because they can help circumvent the restriction inherent in modeling with four layers (M0–M3).
The UML specification acknowledges the definition but does not provide an explanation on how to implement or check the power type mechanism.]]></description><link>model-driven-software-development/03.-advanced-uml.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Model-Driven Software Development/03. Advanced UML.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 02:24:49 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="."&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[02. Metamodelling]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img alt="Pasted image 20251126032239.png" src="attachments/pasted-image-20251126032239.png" target="_self">
Generated by NotebookLM.
Metamodels are special models that make statements about the process of modelling. They describe the possible structure of other models. The originals that a metamodel represents are themselves models. Metamodels are usually prescriptive, meaning they are created before any originals exist, and the creation of these originals is called instantiation.To completely specify a metamodel, its definition must cover four areas: abstract syntax, concrete syntax, static semantics, and dynamic semantics.
Abstract Syntax: The abstract syntax definition describes the structure of models, specifying which constructs, properties, and relations a model consists of. This description is independent of how these constructs are visually presented.
Concrete Syntax: This describes the presentation (e.g., graphical, textual, or file format) of the constructs defined in the abstract syntax. At least one concrete syntax definition is required, but there can be arbitrarily many.
Static Semantics: This describes modelling rules and constraints (such as "no two stations may have the same name") that cannot be expressed in the abstract syntax definition. These constraints are often formulated using languages like OCL, and checking them should be a decidable problem.
Dynamic Semantics: This describes the meaning of the constructs. This definition is often expressed in natural language, although it is possible to formally define dynamic semantics by mapping the metamodel to a formal language with defined semantics, such as finite automata or Petri nets.
Modelling layers represent the hierarchy between models and metamodels. Since a metamodel is itself a model, a metamodel for metamodels (a meta-metamodel) can be defined. In theory, an arbitrary number of layers can be constructed, but in practice, the most abstract layer will eventually become self-descriptive. Approaches exist with a fixed number of layers (e.g., UML) and with variable numbers (multi-level modelling).The four layers often used, particularly in UML and MOF, are distinguished by what they represent or instantiate:
M3 (Meta-Metamodel): Contains concepts that define the structure of M2 (the metamodel layer), such as Class and Attribute. The MOF model is located here.
M2 (Metamodel): Contains concepts that define the structure of M1 (the user model layer), such as Locomotive or Track vehicle. UML 2 is an example of an M2 layer.
M1 (Model): Contains concrete instances that conform to the M2 structure, such as a specific :Locomotive with defined property values (e.g., series=215).
M0 (Original): Represents the artifacts or components of the real world being modelled (e.g., the actual train).
UML (Unified Modelling Language) is an OMG standard that defines a metamodel for software engineering purposes. It is a standard specifying modeling concepts and their relations. It is a graphical standard that includes notational conventions and the UML Diagram Interchange format. While its specification includes semantics definitions in natural language, UML is not a metamodel with formally defined semantics. In version 2.5, UML unified its Superstructure (user-applied constructs) and Infrastructure (basic language constructs) into a single document.UML's foundation is intrinsically linked to the Meta-Object Facility (MOF):
MOF as the M3 Layer: MOF is an OMG standard metadata architecture that serves as the meta-metamodel (M3) for UML.
MOF Specification: MOF includes Complete MOF (CMOF), which is the metamodel used to specify other metamodels, including UML 2.
Cyclic Dependency: There is a cyclic dependency between CMOF and UML, as CMOF is built from Essential MOF (EMOF) and selected elements of the UML metamodel, and simultaneously, UML is specified by CMOF.
UML diagrams are used to model systems, primarily in software engineering, though they can be applied to non-software domains. Key diagrams used to describe systems include:
Class Diagrams: Used to specify domain models and object-oriented designs, showing classes, attributes, operations, and relationships like associations and inheritance.
Object Diagrams: Used to describe the system at a specific point in time by showing instances of classes (instance specifications) and the links between these instances.
Use Case Diagrams: Used to specify the functional requirements of a system, detailing actors (users) and the use cases (functions) they interact with.
Activity Diagrams: Illustrate the flow of an operation or a workflow by showing activities, actions, and control flow.
Sequence Diagrams: Describe the time-ordered message interactions and collaborations between objects or components (lifelines) in a system.
Component Diagrams: Describe the system's high-level physical structure by showing components (such as WebUI or UserManagement) and their dependencies.
]]></description><link>model-driven-software-development/02.-metamodelling.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Model-Driven Software Development/02. Metamodelling.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 02:22:58 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="."&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[07. Sentiment Analysis]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img alt="Pasted image 20251126031330.png" src="attachments/pasted-image-20251126031330.png" target="_self">Sentiment Analysis takes a text sequence with variable length as input and outputs a sentiment label. Tasks range from narrow to broad:
Polarity classification.
User rating (e.g., 1 to 5 stars).
Feature/aspect-based sentiment analysis.
Agreement detection.
Subjectivity/viewpoint detection.
The basic Deep Learning Model uses End-to-end optimization because the Whole network is differentiable.The model generally consists of three main stages:
Encoder: Function to represent a sequence of words as a vector.
Feed Forward Network (FFN): Provides a better representation of the sentence content.
Classification Layer: Outputs the final sentiment label.
The Encoder is composed of three components: Word Embedding, Sequential Layers, and the Aggregation Layer.
Word Embeddings map a word to a dense vector.
This layer often holds the largest number of features in the whole network.
Contrast with One-hot encoding: One-hot encoding results in a large number of features and makes all words equally similar.
Training/Initialization: A common strategy is to use a pre-trained model with fine-tuning. A "no layer" approach, or Bag-of-word representation, fails because Word order does not matter (e.g., "Mary loves John" vs. "John loves Mary").
Since context is important, a model is needed to Process word separately AND Keep the context.
Architectures used for sequential context include Recurrent neural networks (RNNs), Convolution neural networks (CNNs), and Attention networks.
This layer addresses the challenge of converting Variable input size to Fixed output size. Common methods include:
Average word embeddings (meanpool).
Sum word embeddings.
Max pooling ( for the -th dimension).
Last element. Unit: The Vanilla RNN unit takes the Current input and the Previous hidden state .
Properties: RNNs Store history in a vector and capture Global context.
Training: Involves Unfolding the network over time (weights are shared across time steps) and using Backpropagation through time (BPTT).
Issues: RNNs suffer from Vanishing gradients and Exploding gradients (often controlled with clipping).
An Advanced RNN Architecture motivated by the need for a Memory cell.
Mechanism: Uses 1D convolution along the time dimension, also known as Time-delayed neural networks (TDNN).
Filters (Kernels): Act as feature extractors. A filter is a vector in the word vector space that matches a particular region of the space. Filters can be used to capture Uni-gram, Bi-gram, or Tri-gram features (depending on kernel size).
Properties: CNNs exhibit Shift Invariance and capture Local context.
Output: An Aggregation layer (e.g., max-pooling) is used to Reduce to fixed length.
CNNs vs. RNNs: CNNs view context local to the filter width, while RNNs generally look globally. Feed Forward Network (FFN): Input is a Fixed-size representation of the sentence; Output is a Fixed-size representation. The parameters are the Weights of edges between nodes. Classification Layer: Binary Classification: Uses a Single Neuron with the Sigmoid activation function.
Multiclass Classification: Uses One neuron per class with the Softmax activation function (to produce a probability distribution) and Cross-entropy as the loss function. Since the whole network is differentiable, training uses End-to-end optimization. Strategies depend on data and model:
Random initialization.
Frozen pre-trained model.
Pre-trained model with fine-tuning.
]]></description><link>natural-language-processing/07.-sentiment-analysis.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Natural Language Processing/07. Sentiment Analysis.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 02:13:32 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="."&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[06. Topic Models]]></title><description><![CDATA[
Topic models address information overload by helping to Automatically process data. Traditional NLP solutions include Summarization, Information extraction, and Question answering.
Goals: Topic models aim to Cluster/Organize data, Discover hidden themes, and Annotate documents with themes.
Topic Definition: A topic is characterized conceptually by frequent words, and formally as a Distribution over words.
Task: This is an Unsupervised text clustering task. Input: Corpus and the specified Number of Topics ().
Output: The learned Topics (Distribution over words) and Topics per document. The dataset is defined as a Collection of documents.
Document Representation: Individual documents are typically represented using a Bag-of-word representation (a -dimensional vector, where is the vocabulary size).
Collection Representation: A collection of documents is represented as a -dim matrix.
Matrix Values: Matrix values can represent Counts, Indicator function, or TF-IDF.
LSA is a non-probabilistic approach designed to Model which words typically co-occur using matrix representation.
Method: The core idea is to Perform matrix factorization, specifically using SVD (Singular Value Decomposition) to yield Latent Semantic Analysis. represents the Number of topics.
Probabilistic models assume that the observed data is generated by a generative probabilistic process that includes hidden variables. The hidden variable in topic modeling is the Thematic structure. The main task is to Infer hidden structure and Generalize to new data.LDA is the primary probabilistic model used (Blei, 2003).
Name Breakdown: Latent: Topic is unknown / Latent in the text.
Dirichlet: Refers to the Distribution of distributions. Documents are Distributions of topics, and Topics are Distributions of words.
Allocation: Allocate topics to the words. Process/Intuition: Documents exhibit multiple topics. Topics are Distributions over words; Documents are a Mixture of topics; and words are Drawn from one of the topics. The major challenge is that Only documents are observed, while topics are hidden variables.
Graphical Model: This model encodes assumptions and dependencies. Nodes represent random variables, and Shaded nodes () represent the Observed word. Plates indicate replications (e.g., for documents, for words within documents, for topics).
<img alt="Pasted image 20251126030848.png" src="attachments/pasted-image-20251126030848.png" target="_self">
The goal of inference is to compute the posterior distribution conditioned on the documents: .
Variables to Infer: Per-word topic assignment (), Per-document topic proportions (), and Per-corpus topic distribution ().
Challenge: The posterior distribution Cannot be computed exactly due to the intractable marginal likelihood. Even assuming the global variable (Topic, ) is fixed, local inference (for ) remains intractable.
Solution: Approximate methods, such as Gibbs sampling, are necessary.
Gibbs sampling is an iterative Markov Chain Monte Carlo method used for approximation.
Procedure: Start with random assignment of all random variables (topic-word allocation, topic distribution, document distribution).
For a given word, Keep everything except that word fixed.
Assign a topic to this word based on current distribution.
Repeat for several iterations. Sampling Formula: The probability of assigning topic to word is proportional to the product of two components: Document Likelihood: How much document likes topic (). This depends on (Number of times document uses topic ) and (Dirichlet parameter for document to topic distribution).
Topic Likelihood: How much topic likes word (). This depends on (Number of times topic uses word type) and (Dirichlet parameter for topic to word distribution). Evaluating topic models (Unsupervised learning) differs from supervised learning.
Measure 1: Held-out Log Likelihood: A good model should assign a High probability for real data (held-out data).
Measure 2: Word Intrusion: This measure tests topic coherence. A user is presented with the most probable words for a topic, plus a high probability word from another topic (the intruder). The user is asked to find the word that does not belong, and the metric is the Percentage of users who selected the intruder.
Note: Evaluation metrics do not always agree; it is necessary to Measure what you need.
]]></description><link>natural-language-processing/06.-topic-models.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Natural Language Processing/06. Topic Models.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 02:10:16 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="."&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[05. Semantics]]></title><description><![CDATA[We learned from the part 1 that there are multiple NLP tasks. Most of them require the machine to understand the meaning of the sentence and generate corresponding answers. We learned Word2Vec to generate words from part 3. So, today we are going to dive into the study of meaning.Semantics is defined as the Study of meaning. It is distinct from Morphology (how words are built) and Syntax (how words form larger units like phrases/sentences).The field is generally divided into two core branches:
Lexical Semantics: The study of word meaning.
Compositional Semantics: The study of the meaning of sentences.
Lexical semantics (5.1) studies the meaning of words.
Lexeme: The abstract representation of a word (e.g., MOUSE, mice).
Sense: A discrete representation of one aspect of the meaning. The meaning of a word can vary based on the given context (e.g., MOUSE as an animal versus a hand-operated device). Synonyms &amp; Antonyms: Synonyms: Two words with (nearly) identical senses (e.g., couch/sofa). The Principle of contrast suggests that different linguistic forms are always associated with a difference in meaning (e.g., "H2O" is more scientific than "water").
Antonyms: Words with opposing meaning, mostly adjectives (e.g., Long/short, Rise/fall). Taxonomic Relations: Hyponym: A word that is more specific (e.g., Car is a hyponym of vehicle).
Hypernym/Superordinate: A word that is less specific (e.g., Vehicle is a hypernym of car).
<img alt="Pasted image 20251126025836.png" src="attachments/pasted-image-20251126025836.png" target="_self">
Meronym: Represents part-whole relations (e.g., Wheel is a meronym of car).
The Basic Level: Items are "human-sized," have distinctive actions, are learned earliest in childhood, and their names are shortest and most frequent (e.g., "chair" vs. its hypernym "furniture"). Similarity &amp; Relatedness: Word similarity refers to words with different but similar meanings (e.g., Dog and cat). Word embeddings can represent these relationships (e.g., Male-Female, Country-Capital).
Word relatedness refers to words belonging to the same semantic field (e.g., Waiter, Menu, Chef belong to the "restaurants" field). Homonymy: Words that share a form but have unrelated, distinct meanings (e.g., bank1: financial institution; bank2: sloping land). Homographs: Same spelling, different meanings (e.g., bank/bank).
Homophones: Same pronunciation, different meanings (e.g., write/right). Affective meaning involves aspects of a word related to emotion.
Valence: Pleasantness of the stimulus (e.g., Happy/satisfied vs. unhappy/annoyed).
Arousal: Intensity of emotion (e.g., Excited vs. calm).
Dominance: Degree of control (e.g., Controlling vs. influenced). Description: A hierarchically organized lexical database that acts as an on-line thesaurus and dictionary.
Definition of Sense: Defined by a Synset (synonym set), which is a set of near-synonyms that instantiates a sense or concept, with an accompanying gloss.<br>
<img alt="Pasted image 20251126025850.png" src="attachments/pasted-image-20251126025850.png" target="_self">
Structure: WordNet can be viewed as a graph where nodes are synsets and edges represent various relationships, such as "is-a" (hypernym/hyponym).
Supersenses: Top-level hypernyms in the hierarchy (e.g., Noun supersenses include GROUP, PERSON, ARTIFACT).
Challenges: Resolving Ambiguity (one form, multiple meanings split form) and Variability (multiple forms, one meaning merge forms).
Compositional semantics (5.2) studies the meaning of sentences. The central challenge is the infinite number of sentences.
Frege's Principle of compositionality: The meaning of an expression depends on the meaning of its parts and how they are put together.
This involves structuring meaning using symbols, bridging the gap between language and common-sense knowledge.
Vocabulary: Includes Non-logical (open-ended terms linked to a world model) and Logical (closed set of symbols, operators, quantifiers) elements.
Examples of Representations: First-order logic, Abstract Meaning Representation (AMR), and Frame-based/slot-filling representation.
Requirements: Verifiability: Ability to compare the represented state to the state of the world (e.g., checking Serves(Maharani, VegetarianFood) against a knowledge base).
Unambiguous representations: The representation itself must be clear, even if the natural language sentence is vague.
Canonical Form: Distinct inputs with the same meaning must yield the same representation.
Inference and Variables: Variables are needed to make general statements, and the system must use world knowledge to draw conclusions.
Expressiveness: Must handle a wide range of expressions. This is a flexible and well-understood meaning representation. It uses Terms (objects), Functions (e.g., LocationOf(Frasca)), and Variables to make general statements.Shallow semantics aims to represent the commonality of an event despite its linguistic variability (e.g., different ways to describe a stock purchase).
Thematic Roles: Identify common roles like AGENT (often the subject) and THEME.
Challenges: Fragmentations (e.g., multiple types of INSTRUMENTS) and difficulty in defining roles (e.g., whether an Agent must be animate).
Alternatives: Use broader roles like PROTO-AGENT (Agent-like properties) and PROTO-PATIENT (Patient-like properties). PropBank (Proposition Bank) (5.2.4): A dataset based on Penn TreeBank annotation, focusing primarily on verbs.
Uses numbered roles (Arg0, Arg1, etc.) specific to each verb sense. Arg0 typically represents the PROTO-AGENT, and Arg1 the PROTO-PATIENT.
ArgMs represent modifications like time (TMP), location (LOC), or reason (PRP/CAU). FrameNet (5.2.5): Motivated by the need for inference about situations described by different verbs (e.g., increased vs. rose).
Defines Frames as background knowledge structures containing common-sense information about a situation (e.g., Change_position_on_a_scale).
Uses Core roles that are specific to the frame, and Non-core roles (general properties) comparable to PropBank's Arg_M. Reasoning (5.3) takes Facts and Logic as input to generate an Answer.
Deductive Reasoning: Moves from premise(s) to a Firm conclusion using logic (e.g., All whales are mammals All whales have kidneys). (general -&gt; special)
Inductive Reasoning: Moves from observation to a Likely conclusion (e.g., winged creatures are usually birds this winged creature is likely a bird). (special -&gt; general)
Abductive Reasoning: Moves from observation to a Likely explanation.
Formal Reasoning: Follows formal rules/logic and is based on axiomatic knowledge.
Informal Reasoning: Uses intuition, experience, and common sense. Goal: An applied semantic inference task aimed at identifying the logical relationship between a pair of text sequences (a Premise and a Hypothesis).
Also called: Textual Entailment.
Labels: Entailment: Hypothesis is true.
Contradiction: Hypothesis is false.
Neutral (Undetermined): Hypothesis is undetermined. ]]></description><link>natural-language-processing/05.-semantics.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Natural Language Processing/05. Semantics.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 02:03:40 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="."&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[04. Sentence Structure]]></title><description><![CDATA[Part-of-Speech (POS): POS tags classify words based on their grammatical relationship and functional category (e.g., noun, verb) in context. This differs from word sense (meaning).
Classification: Words belong to Open classes (lexical words) (Nouns, Verbs, Adjectives, etc.) or Closed classes (functional) (Determiners, Pronouns, Conjunctions).
Universal Tag Set: Smaller, coarser sets (like the 12-tag Universal Tag Set) are used for cross-lingual purposes.
Challenge (Ambiguity): Many word instances are ambiguous, meaning the same word type can have multiple POS tags (e.g., "back" can be JJ, NN, RB, or VB). POS tagging is the process of determining the correct tag for a word given its context.
Syntax studies how words organize into hierarchical units called constituents (phrases). Only entire phrases, such as a Prepositional Phrase (PP), can be moved within a sentence. Context Free Grammar: Introduced by Chomsky, CFG is a formal system used to generate sentences and assign parse trees. Non-terminals () are phrase variables (NP, VP), and Terminals () are the actual words. Phrase Structure Grammar: This applies CFG rules to define natural language structures (e.g., Declarative sentences are NP VP). Subcategorization: Verbs enforce constraints on the required accompanying phrases; e.g., Transitive verbs require a direct object, while Intransitive verbs do not.
Ambiguity: A sentence can have multiple correct parse trees (Structural Ambiguity). This includes Attachment ambiguity and Coordination ambiguity. Lexicalized Grammars (e.g., Combinatory Categorial Grammar): These models use a lexicon to encode complex grammatical dependencies like Agreement, Subcategorization, and Long-distance dependencies. Words are assigned detailed categories (e.g., the verb "Cancel" has the category ). Forward rule application ()
Backward rule application ()
<img alt="Pasted image 20251126025040.png" src="attachments/pasted-image-20251126025040.png" target="_self"> Dependency Grammar: This approach describes structure using directed binary relations (typed relations) between a head and its dependent. Graph : Vertices correspond to words
: Arcs corresponding to relations Restrictions: Connected
Designated root node
<br>Acyclic (connected acyclic graph is a tree) or planar <img alt="Pasted image 20251126025053.png" src="attachments/pasted-image-20251126025053.png" target="_self"> Language Models automatically learn sentence structure by assigning a Probability to a sentence.Simple counting fails due to sparse data; many valid but unseen sentences are assigned a probability of zero.Solution: Chain Rule.E.g.,Estimating the probability of a word from its full history is intractable.Solution: Markov Assumption.
The probability of a word depends only on the previous words.N-gram Models: Unigram, Bigram, Trigram, etc. Though insufficient for capturing long-distance dependencies, they are practical.<br><img alt="Pasted image 20251126025309.png" src="attachments/pasted-image-20251126025309.png" target="_self">MLE estimates N-gram probabilities by maximizing the likelihood of training data.<br><img alt="Pasted image 20251126025315.png" src="attachments/pasted-image-20251126025315.png" target="_self">A key challenge persists: if an N-gram is an unseen event (count = 0), its probability is 0, making the entire sentence probability 0.If you'd like, I can also format these into a printable PDF, add color themes, or convert into study flashcards.]]></description><link>natural-language-processing/04.-sentence-structure.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Natural Language Processing/04. Sentence Structure.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 01:57:31 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="."&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[03. Neural Word Representation]]></title><description><![CDATA[NLP has undergone a major transformation over the past few decades, shifting from traditional statistical methods to modern neural network-based approaches.Early NLP systems relied heavily on statistical language models (SLMs). These models estimate the probability of a word sequence based on observed frequencies in large text corpora. N-gram models is one of the most common approaches, which predict the next word given the previous n−1 words. For example, a trigram model predicts the next word based on the previous two words.However, SLMs have limitations about data sparsity, context window, and feature engineering (SLMs often required manual preprocessing and feature extraction).In the part, we will focus on neural network based methods.Word Embedding is one of Dense Embeddings. Dense vector has the following advantages: Short vectors may be easier to use as features in machine learning (less weights to tune) Dense vectors may generalize better than storing explicit counts They may do better at capturing synonymy: car and automobile are synonyms; but are distinct dimensions
a word with car as a neighbor and a word with automobile as a neighbor should be similar, but aren’t In practice, they appear to work better So can we convert one-hot (Sparse) to Dense Embeddings? Assume there is a matrix W. We can multiply our one-hot with W. This gives us the “embedding” for a word. W is what we need to learn (in the context of machine learning).
Please read Q&amp;A for more details. Word2Vec CBOW Skip-gram Negative sampling Fasttext character representation Glove Q: What is the relationship between the corpus-based approach and feature engineering? A: In traditional Corpus-based Approaches to NLP, feature extraction is an explicit process. This feature extraction defines the features used by the statistical model, such as the word ID, case, and POS tags (e.g., Word: 546; Case: Upper-case; POS: NN). In Deep Learning Approaches, the input text still undergoes feature extraction, but the output is a dense binary vector (e.g., 10010010010101). Therefore, feature engineering is the traditional method of explicit feature extraction from the corpus, which has been largely replaced by automatic feature learning in deep learning.Q: What is an important property of word embeddings? A: An important property of word embeddings is that semantic similar words should have similar representation. This concept is tied to J.R. Firth’s 1953 dictum: “You shall know a word by the company it keeps!”.Q: What determines the size of one-hot embeddings? A: The size, or dimension, of a one-hot encoding vector is determined by the vocabulary size.Q: What is an advantage of dense embeddings? A: Dense vectors have several advantages: they are short vectors, may generalize better, and appear to work better in practice, especially at capturing synonymy.Q: What is a problem with n-gram models? A: A major problem with statistical N-gram models is that most longer word sequences have not been seen in the corpus. This requires a non-satisfactory solution like back-off to a shorter sequence. N-gram models also operate in Discrete Space.Q: Why do we call the Feed Forward Neural Network here self-supervised? A: The Feed Forward Neural Network language model is considered self-supervised because training needs only unlabelled data (pure text). The model is trained to predict the next word given previous words. The meaning of the word is important for estimating the next word, and this meaning needs to be encoded in the embedding.Q: What is the advantage of a continuous space? A: The advantage of mapping words to a continuous word representation is generalization to similar n-grams. Unlike discrete space, which only allows for exact matching, continuous space enables the model to automatically learn optimal features and find the nearest neighbor, capturing syntactic similarities and semantic similarities.Q: Is the position of the input words important? A: For the Continuous Bag of Words Model (CBOW), the position of the input words is ignored. The model sums the surrounding words to predict the center word.Q: How many embeddings do we get for each word? A: For Word2Vec models (CBOW and Skip-gram), typically there is one embedding for each word.
More details: <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://lilianweng.github.io/posts/2017-10-15-word-embedding/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://lilianweng.github.io/posts/2017-10-15-word-embedding/" target="_self">Learning Word Embedding</a> <br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://medium.com/@fraidoonomarzai99/word2vec-cbow-skip-gram-in-depth-88d9cc340a50" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://medium.com/@fraidoonomarzai99/word2vec-cbow-skip-gram-in-depth-88d9cc340a50" target="_self">Word2Vec (CBOW, Skip-gram) In Depth</a> Q: What is the CBOW score function based on? A: The CBOW score function is based on the dot product to measure similarity.Q: What is the difference between CBOW and Skip-gram? A: CBOW and Skip-gram have opposite objectives:
CBOW predicts the word based on surrounding words.
Skip-gram predicts the surrounding words given the current word.
Q: What is maximized with the Skip-gram objective? A: The Skip-gram objective is to maximize the probability of any context word given the current word. This objective uses a negative log loss.Q: Why is negative sampling necessary? A: Negative sampling is necessary because the standard Skip-gram objective requires normalization over the entire vocabulary, which is computationally demanding. Negative sampling resolves this by generating samples and summing over those samples instead of the entire vocabulary.Q: Why do we use sigmoid instead of softmax in the objective function? A: We use the Sigmoid function () because negative sampling converts the problem from a multiclass classifier to a binary classifier.Q: Where do we get negative examples from? A: Negative examples are sampled from the lexicon. The negative set typically contains 2 to 20 words sampled from some distribution, such as uniform, unigram, or a smoothed unigram. The smoothed unigram distribution is created by raising the probabilities to the power of and then renormalizing.Q: For a corpus with fixed size, are there more unique 6-grams or 3-grams? A: Based on the problem of N-gram models—that most longer word sequences have not been seen—it can be inferred that there would be more unique 6-grams than 3-grams, as longer sequences lead to higher sparsity.Q: How are context and target words represented with FastText? A: FastText uses character N-grams:A: FastText uses character N-grams:
The word embedding for the target word is the sum of character 3-grams to 6-grams and the whole word itself.
The word embedding for the context word is taken from the embedding table without adding character n-grams.
Q: What is the difference between Word2Vec and FastText? A: FastText is an extension of Word2Vec that addresses challenges found in Word2Vec. FastText uses subword representation (character n-grams) to solve issues in morphologically rich languages and to create representations for words that have not been seen previously.Q: What is a key difference between Word2Vec and GloVe? A: The key difference lies in the perspective used for training: Word2Vec uses a Local view (predicting words within the context), while GloVe uses a Global view. GloVe leverages Word co-occurrence matrices and is motivated by the ratio of co-occurrence probabilities.Q: In which situations does GloVe likely produce unreliable word embeddings?
Rare words – too few co-occurrences to learn meaningful vectors.
Small corpus – global statistics are sparse and noisy.
Domain mismatch – training domain differs from the target domain.
Polysemous words – one vector cannot represent multiple senses.
No subword modeling – fails on morphology and misspellings.
Out-of-vocabulary words – no embeddings for unseen words.
Biased training data – co-occurrence statistics reflect and amplify bias.
]]></description><link>natural-language-processing/03.-neural-word-representation.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Natural Language Processing/03. Neural Word Representation.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 01:44:46 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[02. Words]]></title><description><![CDATA[Example (Chinese): 我看书 — “I read/look at a book.”. Morphemes:
我 = I
看 = read/look
书 = book
Key idea: Minimal or no inflection; morphemes usually stand alone.Example (Turkish): ev-ler-in-de — “in your houses”. Morphemes:
ev = house
-ler = plural
-in = your
-de = in
Key idea: Morphemes have clear boundaries and single meanings, attached in sequence.Example (Spanish): habl-o — “I speak”. Morphemes:
habl- = speak
-o = 1st person + singular + present
Key idea: A single morpheme typically encodes multiple grammatical features.Example (Inuktitut): tusaatsiarunnanngittualuujunga — “I really can’t hear well”. Simplified morphemes:
tusaa- = hear
-tsiaq- = well
-junnaq- = be able
-nngit- = not
-tualuu- = very
-junga = I
Key idea: Many morphemes combine to express what would be a whole sentence.Example (Arabic): kitaab — “book”. Morphemes:
k-t-b = root “write”
i__a__ = vocalic pattern forming a noun
Key idea: Words are formed by inserting vocalic patterns into consonantal roots.
Lexeme, e.g., SEE
Word-form, e.g., saw, seeing, saws
Paradigm, e.g., I, my, mine, me
Word family, e.g., act, action, actor, activate, active, activist Lexical/Content
Functional
Root Suffix
Prefix
Infix
Circumfix Changes the grammatical form of a word without creating a new lexeme.
Does not change core meaning or word class.
Typical categories: tense, number, case, agreement.
Examples:
walk → walks (3sg)
cat → cats (plural)
see → saw (past) Forms a new word (new lexeme) by adding derivational affixes.
Often changes meaning and sometimes word class.
Examples:
happy → unhappy
nation → national
modern → modernize
read → reader Combines two or more roots/words to form a new lexeme.
The components remain recognizable.
Examples:
black + board → blackboard
sun + light → sunlight
ice + cream → ice-cream
Here’s a concise English note summarizing the morphological processes you listed, with clear examples:
Maps a word form to its lemma (dictionary/base form).
Ignores context.
Example:
saw → see Lemma and Lexeme are different. Lexeme is an abstract concept, while lemma is a concrete concept. Breaks a word into (lemma + grammatical tag).
Does not consider context, so may produce multiple analyses.
Example:
saw → {(see, verb.past), (saw, noun.sg)} Uses context to select the correct analysis.
Example:
Sentence: Peter saw her
saw → {(see, verb.past)} Splits a word into its smallest meaningful units (morphemes).
Example:
de-nation-al-iz-ation → de + nation + al + iz + ation Produces a word form from a lemma + features.
Essentially the reverse of lemmatization.
Example:
(see, verb.past) → saw
Both Feature Engineering (FE) and Representation Learning (RL) are methodologies designed to solve the critical challenge in machine learning models: how to map text into a fixed vector representation, or .However, they differ fundamentally in their approach, timeframe, and resulting data structure.Feature Engineering (FE) represents the dominant methods used over the last 25 years. This approach relies on manually defined templates to describe the important information of the text. FE is often decried as “costly, hand-crafted, expensive, domain-specific,” among other criticisms. While simple features typically give the bulk of the performance and can yield high accuracies, the feature set is still difficult to maintain.Representation Learning (RL) describes the methods developed over the last 10 years. The defining characteristic of RL is that the features are automatically learned. The result of this process is an approximation, meaning some information are lost, and the representation is typically task dependent.The methodologies lead to stark differences in the resulting vector format:
FE commonly uses representations like the Bag of Words (BoW). This approach results in a Sparse matrix, where most entries are zero. BoW uses one feature per word, which can be a Binary feature (0 or 1) or a Count feature. Feature Importance and TF-IDF can help solve problems respectively about word importance and high-frequently used no-meaning words.
RL generates a Neural representation, which is characterized as Dense. Negation: It's not a great monster movie.
Different sense: There's a great deal of corny dialogue and preposterous moments.
Multiple sentiments: A great ensemble cast can't lift this heartfelt enterprise out of the familiar.
Number of features: Too few. Hard to distinguish different inputs
Too many. Overfitting Representation Learning evolved to better handle critical challenges inherent in text data that constrained Feature Engineering:
Word Order and Length: FE methods like BoW ignore word position when dealing with variable length input. Although FE can use Higher-Order Binary Feature Templates (like bigrams or trigrams) to consider word order and maintain a fixed size vector representation, this introduces the challenge of an extremely large number of features. Conversely, RL must address the fact that word order is important and must handle variable length input.
Open Vocabulary: For FE, open vocabulary is a challenge that requires the use of a fixed vocab. RL also faces the open vocabulary challenge, but aims to solve it by being able to understand unknown words, such as the complex term Hippopotomonstrosesquipedaliophobia.
Granularity: RL’s approach to solving vocabulary challenges involves identifying the best granularity—choosing among words, subwords, or characters. RL acknowledges that while using characters provides much training data and allows understanding of unknown words, it leads to long sequences for text, which is not efficient. Therefore, RL uses machine learning based subword segmentation to learn efficient representation. Techniques like Byte-Pair Encoding (BPE), which starts with an Initial vocabulary of characters to ensure every words can be represented, are employed to strike this balance.
]]></description><link>natural-language-processing/02.-words.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Natural Language Processing/02. Words.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 01:29:45 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[01. Introduction]]></title><description><![CDATA[NLP: Algorithms to process, analyze and understand texts in natural language
Understanding structure
Understanding meaning Ambiguity, e.g., bank
Compositionality, e.g., green thumb
Co-reference, e.g., if the baby does not like the milk, boil it
Living language, e.g., Eyjafjallajökull
Rare events
<img alt="Pasted image 20251126022044.png" src="attachments/pasted-image-20251126022044.png" target="_self">
Corpus = large collection of annotated texts (or speech files)
Linguistics
Machine learning
NLP tasks: Information Extraction + Retrieval
Summarization
Machine translation
Question Answering
Personal assistant NLP techniques (focus on deep learning-based): Data types Texts, e.g., Brown Corpus, Penn Treebank
Dictionaries/Ontologies, e.g., WordNet, GermaNet, EuroWordNet Data grows English Text Corpora (News)
Computer MT or ASR systems train on &gt;&gt; 1GWords. News Shuffle, GigaWord, Europarl, VideoLectures, …
Human speaks 0.5 GigaWords in a Lifetime! Model types Classification, e.g., word sense disambiguation
Sequence Classification, e.g., sentiment analysis
Sequence labeling, e.g., named entity recognition
Sequence to Sequence model, e.g., summerization
Structure prediction, e.g., parsing Evaluation: Human evaluation
Automatic evaluation ]]></description><link>natural-language-processing/01.-introduction.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Natural Language Processing/01. Introduction.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 01:20:46 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="."&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>